A Guide to the Records of the Arlington County Volunteer Fire Department, 1919-2001
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Records of the Arlington County Volunteer Fire Department, 1919-2001
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 4
15 boxes.
Arlington County Volunteer Fire Department
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Largely a gift of Harold LeRoy and Vincent Del Giudice
Historical Information
Arlington County has seven volunteer fire departments that help the official county fire department respond to fire and medical emergencies, assist in public education demonstrations, and participate in fundraising activities, administrative duties, and equipment maintenance, among other duties. These volunteer companies began around the start of the 20th century in response to the growing need for organization during a fire emergency. These volunteer companies were eventually supplanted by career firefighters who worked for the County Fire Department, and the volunteers became supplemental staff. The volunteers assist during a large emergency or staff additional units during peak call periods. Each volunteer company has its own staff and board; they also own fire and EMT equipment and vehicles. Many of these companies built station houses at the time of their incorporation; Station 3 (Cherrydale) is on the national and state registers of historic landmarks.
In the 1920s, the individual volunteer fire companies decided to form an association for mutual education and benefit: the Arlington County Fireman's Association. Besides organizing training sessions for the county's volunteer firefighters, it also sponsors many social events such as an annual dance in the spring and a summer/early fall barbeque.
As of 2005, these are the Arlington County volunteer fire departments:
Station 1: Arlington
Station 2: Ballston
Station 3: Cherrydale
Station 4: Clarendon
Station 5: Jefferson District (Aurora Hills)
Station 6: Falls Church, serving both Arlington and Fairfax Counties and Falls Church City
Station 7: Fairlington
Scope and Content
This collection contains materials from both Volunteer Department #5 (Jefferson District) and the Arlington County Fireman's Association (ACFA). The donor has been heavily involved with the ACFA and Department #5, and these papers reflect his involvement. However, as new materials from other departments arrive, they will be added to this collection. The entire collection currently measures 6.26 linear feet.
The Department #5 materials cover the years 1926 to 1996, but the bulk date from the 1950s to the 1970s. There are chronological files that contained meeting minutes, receipts, vouchers for purchases and other administrative documents. Loose material includes membership materials, correspondence, notes, and financial records that were not included in the chronological files. There are many vouchers and accompanying receipts for money spent by volunteers on things like food and equipment. The activity logs hold sheets filled out every time the volunteers went on a call. They are split into fire calls and first aid calls. These sheets contain information such as address and names involved in the emergency, extent of damage, medical actions taken, staff on the call, and notes. There are also duty logs for the department, where staff signed in and out and made notations on activities done around the station house.
The ACFA materials focus on Harold LeRoy's activities organizing the association's social gatherings. This subgroup covers 1960 to 2001, and the bulk of the material is from the 1990s. There are administrative records such as meeting minutes, by-laws and correspondence, but the bulk of the material are receipts and contracts created while putting together training sessions for Volunteer Fire Department members and a variety of social events.
There are a small amount of photographs in each subgroup, showing actual emergencies, new vehicles and equipment, training sessions, and the ACFA baseball team in action. There is also a small amount of material from other departments filed at the end of the collection.
Arrangement
This collection has three subgroups, each split into several series. Subgroup 1 has the records for Department #5. Series 1 contains the chronological files for the department. They are labeled and arranged in the manner originally formed by Department #5. In Series 1, portions of folder titles in brackets ([]) have been added by the archivist for clarification. The subsequent eight series, for a total of nine, are arranged by the archivist according to type of material: Constitution and By-Laws, Membership, Financial Records, Correspondence, Events, Activity and Log Books, Trial Board, and Miscellaneous. Photographs have been filed in Series 9, Miscellaneous. Any folders or envelopes labeled by a member of Department #5 in all series except Series 1 are put into quotes (''"); otherwise, the archivist created the folder titles for these series.
Subgroup 2 holds the records for the Arlington County Fireman's Association, and is split into four series. This subgroup was arranged by the archivist according to the subject and type of the material. The four series are Administrative Files, Training, Events, and Photographs. Series 3, Events, is split into three subseries, Spring Dinner Dance, Summer Barbeque, and Other Events. The material for Series 2, Training, and Series 3, Events, was originally filed in envelopes with the event name and date written on them. In these cases, the title of the folder reflects the title written on the envelope, and is put into quotes ("").
Subgroup 3 has some materials relating to other companies and has been sorted by company. As additional materials are donated, this Subgroup will expand.
There are some oversized materials in this collection, which have been moved to appropriate housing. Separation sheets have been added to mark their original placement. An asterisk (*) at the end of the folder title denotes oversize materials found in this location.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Other Finding Aid
RG 82, The Personal Papers of Herb and Mayme Smith
Other Finding Aid
RG 32 County Manager's Library, Subgroup 2, Fire Department
Subjects:
Fire departments.; Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.); Volunteer fire fighters; Volunteer fire departments
Contents List
- Records of Jefferson District Volunteer Fire Department #5
  - Chronological files
    - [Meeting Minutes, 1933-1935] (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Meetings 1946 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Meetings, 1947 [1943-1945] (Box 1)
    - [Disbursement Vouchers, 1946-1947] (Box 1)
    - Minutes 1948 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Meetings 1949 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Meetings 1950 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Meetings 1951 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Meetings 1952 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Meetings [Vouchers] 1952 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Meetings, 1953 [1] (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Meetings, 1953 [2] (Box 2)
    - Vouchers [Accounts Disbursement, January-June] 1953 (Box 2)
    - Vouchers [Accounts Disbursement, July-December] 1953 (Box 2)
    - Vouchers [Accounts Received] 1953 (Box 2)
    - [Meeting Attendance Sheets] 1954 (Box 2)
    - Minutes of Meetings 1954 (Box 2)
    - Vouchers [Accounts Disbursement, January-June] 1954 (Box 2)
    - Vouchers [Accounts Disbursement, July-December] 1954 (Box 2)
    - Vouchers [Accounts Received] 1954 (Box 2)
    - 1955 (Box 2)
    - [Canceled Checks] 1955 (Box 2)
    - [Vouchers, January-June] 1954 (Box 2)
    - [Vouchers, July-December] 1955 (Box 3)
    - Board of Directors Minutes 1955 (Box 3)
    - Company Meeting Minutes 1956 (Box 3)
    - 1956 (Box 3)
    - [Meeting Minutes] 1956 (Box 3)
    - [Vouchers - Accounts Disbursement] 1956 (Box 3)
    - [Vouchers - Accounts Received] 1956 (Box 3)
    - 1957 (Box 3)
    - [First Aid Squad Report, August] 1957 (Box 3)
    - [Vouchers - Accounts Disbursement, January-June] 1957 (Box 2)
    - [Vouchers - Accounts Disbursement, July-December] 1957 (Box 3)
    - Vouchers [Accounts Received] 1957 (Box 3)
    - Minutes and Vouchers 1958 (Box 3)
    - Minutes and Vouchers [Accounts Disbursement, January-June] 1958 (Box 3)
    - Minutes and Vouchers [Accounts Disbursement, July-December] 1958 (Box 3)
    - Minuts and Vouchers [Accounts Received] 1958 (Box 3)
    - Vouchers and Minutes 1959 (Box 4)
    - Vouchers [Accounts Disbursement] and Minutes, [January-June] 1959 (Box 4)
    - Vouchers [Accounts Disbursement] and Minutes, [July-December] 1959 (Box 4)
    - Vouchers [Accounts Received] 1959 (Box 4)
    - Minutes and Vouchers 1960 (Box 4)
    - Minutes and Vouchers [Accounts Disbursement, January-May] 1960 (Box 4)
    - Minutes and Vouchers [Accounts Disbursement, June-December] 1960 (Box 4)
    - Minutes and Vouchers [Accounts Received] 1960 (Box 4)
    - Vouchers and Minutes 1961 (Box 4)
    - Vouchers [Accounts Disbursement] and Minutes, [January-April] 1961 (Box 4)
    - Vouchers [Accounts Disbursement] and Minutes, [May-August] 1961 (Box 4)
    - Vouchers [Accounts Disbursement] and Minutes, [September - December] 1961 (Box 5)
    - Vouchers [Accounts Received] 1961 (Box 5)
    - 1962 (Box 5)
    - [Vouchers, Accounts Disbursement, January-April] 1962 (Box 5)
    - [Vouchers, Accounts Disbursement, May-August] 1962 (Box 5)
    - [Vouchers, Accounts Disbursement, September-December] 1962 (Box 5)
    - [Vouchers, Accounts Received] 1962 (Box 5)
    - Minutes and Miscellaneous Papers 1963 (Box 5)
    - Minutes and Miscellaneous Papers [Accounts Disbursement] 1963 (Box 5)
    - Minutes and Miscellaneous Papers [Accounts Received] 1963 (Box 5)
    - Minutes and Records 1964 (Box 5)
    - Minutes and Records, [Meeting Minutes] 1964 (Box 5)
    - Minutes and Records [Accounts Disbursement, January-June] 1964 (Box 6)
    - Minutes and Records [Accounts Disbursement, July-December] 1964 (Box 6)
    - Minutes and Records [Accounts Received] 1964 (Box 6)
    - 1965 (Box 6)
    - [Vouchers, Accounts Disbursement, January-June] 1965 (Box 6)
    - Vouchers, Accounts Disbursement, July-December] 1965 (Box 6)
    - Vouchers, Accounts Received] 1965 (Box 6)
    - 1966 (Box 6)
    - [Vouchers, Accounts Disbursement] 1966 (Box 6)
    - [Vouchers, Accounts Received] 1966 (Box 6)
    - 1967 (Box 6)
    - [Vouchers] 1967 (Box 6)
    - [Bank Statements/Canceled Checks] 1967 (Box 7)
    - 1968 (Box 7)
    - [Meeting Minutes] 1968 (Box 7)
    - 1970* (Box 7)
    - [Bank Statements/Canceled Checks] 1970 (Box 7)
    - [Vouchers, Accounts Disbursement, January-June] 1970 (Box 7)
    - [Vouchers, Accounts Disbursements, July-December] 1970 (Box 7)
    - [Vouchers, Accounts Received] 1971 (Box 7)
    - 1971 (Box 7)
    - [Bank Statements/Canceled Checks] 1971 (Box 7)
    - [Vouchers, Accounts Disbursement, January-June] 1971 (Box 7)
    - [Vouchers, Accounts Disbursement, July-December] 1971 (Box 8)
    - [Vouchers, Accounts Received] 1971 (Box 8)
    - 1972 (Box 8)
    - [Vouchers, Accounts Disbursement] 1972 (Box 8)
    - [Vouchers, Accounts Received] 1972 (Box 8)
    - 1975 (Box 8)
    - [Vouchers, Accounts Disbursement] 1975 (Box 8)
    - [Vouchers, Accounts Received] 1975 (Box 8)
    - 1977 (Box 8)
    - 1978 (Box 8)
    - [Bank Statements] 1978 (Box 8)
    - [Canceled Checks] 1978 (Box 8)
    - [Vouchers] 1978 (Box 8)
    - 1979 (Box 8)
    - Minutes, etc. 1983 (Box 8)
    - Minutes, etc., [Meeting Minutes] 1983 (Box 9)
    - Minutes, etc., [Vouchers] 1983 (Box 9)
    - [1984] (Box 9)
    - [Meeting Minutes, 1984] (Box 9)
    - [Vouchers, 1984] (Box 9)
    - 1985 (Box 9)
    - [Meeting Minutes] 1985 (Box 9)
    - [Vouchers] 1985 (Box 9)
    - Minutes, etc. 1983 (Box 9)
    - [Meeting Minutes], Records 1987 (Box 9)
    - [Vouchers], Records 1987 (Box 9)
  - Constitution and By-Laws
    - Certificate of Incorporation 1919 (Box 9)
    - Constitution and By-Laws 1950, 1951, 1976 (Box 9)
    - Constitution and By-Laws with LeRoy Annotations 1946, 1976, 1981, 1985, 1986, 1988 (Box 10)
  - Membership
    - Membership 1952 (Box 10)
    - Co. 5 Honor Roll (Box 10)
  - Financial Records
    - Bank Statements/Canceled Checks 1968 (Box 10)
    - Bond Certificates 1928[1] (Box 10)
    - Bond Certificates 1928[2] (Box 10)
    - Bond Sale Receipts 1928 (Box 10)
    - Receipts, "Asst. Receipts Co. 5" 1991-1992 (Box 10)
    - Receipts, "Co. 5 Blank Checks and Receipts" 1993-1994 (Box 10)
    - Receipts, "EMT Cours" 1993 (Box 10)
    - Vouchers 1946-1947 (Box 10)
    - Vouchers 1948 (Box 10)
    - Vouchers 1949 (Box 10)
    - Vouchers 1950 (Box 10)
    - Vouchers 1951 (Box 11)
    - Vouchers 1967[1] (Box 11)
    - Vouchers 1967[2] (Box 11)
    - Vouchers 1968[1] (Box 11)
    - Vouchers 1968[2] (Box 11)
    - Vouchers 1977 (Box 11)
    - Vouchers 1979 (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous 1956, 1968 (Box 11)
    - Account Books 1928-1931, 1947-1960 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence 1927-1930 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence (Typed Copies) 1927-1930 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence 1945-1948, 1950-1952, 1972, 1977, 1992 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence, Miscellaneous 1946, 1949 (Box 12)
  - Events
    - 70th Anniversary Dinner 1996 (Box 12)
    - "Annual Dinner" 1986 (Box 12)
    - "Annual Dinner" 1991 (Box 12)
    - "Annual Dinner" 1992 (Box 12)
    - "Annual Dinner" 1994 (Box 12)
    - "Association Meeting" 1992 (Box 12)
    - "Association Meeting" 1994 (Box 12)
    - "Association Meeting" 1996 (Box 12)
    - "Dinner Dance" 1982 (Box 12)
    - "Dinner Dance" 1983 (Box 12)
    - "Dinner Dance" 1984 (Box 12)
    - "F.F.I. Expenses" 1992 (Box 12)
    - Calendar 1985 (Box 12)
  - Activity and Log Books
    - Log Books 1931-1969 (Box 12)
    - Activity Reports, January-June 1951 (Box 12)
    - Activity Reports, July-September 1951 (Box 12)
    - Activity Reports, October-December 1951 (Box 12)
    - Activity Reports, January-March 1952 (Box 12)
    - Activity Reports, April-May 1952 (Box 12)
    - Activity Reports, June-July 1952 (Box 13)
    - Activity Reports, August-October 1952 (Box 13)
    - Activity Reports, November-December 1952 (Box 13)
    - Activity Reports, November-December 1957 (Box 13)
    - Activity Reports, Miscellaneous 1952, 1954, n.d. (Box 13)
  - Trial Board
    - "Trial Board - James Douglas," August-September 1994 (Box 13)
    - "Trial Board - Pifilo," November 1994 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous
    - State Corporation Commission 1950, 1979 (Box 13)
    - "Certificate of Incorporation of Arlington-Fairfax Fireman's Association" 1928 (Box 13)
    - Fire Calls 1926, 1927 (Box 13)
    - Virginia Law on Lights and Sirens, n.d. (Box 13)
    - "Smuzynski - Fire Department Sale of Old Building" 1976-1978, 1986 (Box 13)
    - Photographs 1960, n.d. (Box 13)
- Arlington County Fireman's Association
  - Administrative Files
    - By-Laws with LeRoy Annotations (1) 1981, 1989 (Box 13)
    - By-Laws with LeRoy Annotations (2) 1960, 1981, n.d. (Box 13)
    - Correspondence 1992 (Box 13)
    - Meeting Minutes 1926-27 (Box 13)
    - Membership, "Binns Problem" 1992 (Box 14)
    - Membership, "Patricia Copeland - Dropped) 1992 (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous 1990, 1998, n.d. (Box 14)
    - "Steward's Fund" 1994-1997 (Box 14)
    - Supplies 1982, 1998 (Box 14)
  - Training
    - "B. L. S. Training Course" 1995 (Box 14)
    - "E. M. T. Course" 1996 (Box 14)
    - "F. F. I Course" 1994 (Box 14)
    - "F. F. I Course" 1996 (Box 14)
    - F. F. I/II Course" 1995 (Box 14)
    - "Firefighter II Expenses" 1992 (Box 14)
    - "Hazmat Course and F. F. I and II Certification" 1992 (Box 14)
  - Events
    - Spring Dinner Dance
      - "Dinner Dance - 50th" 1985 (Box 14)
      - "Dinner Dance" 1987 (Box 14)
      - "Dinner Dance" 1988 (Box 14)
      - "Dinner Dance" 1989 (Box 14)
      - "Dinner Dance" 1990 (Box 14)
      - "Dinner Dance" 1991 (Box 14)
      - "Dinner Dance" 1992 (Box 14)
      - "Dinner Dance" 1993 (Box 14)
      - "Dinner Dance" 1994 (Box 14)
      - "Dinner Dance" 1995 (Box 14)
      - "Dinner Dance" 1996 (Box 14)
      - "Dinner Dance" 1997 (Box 14)
      - "Dinner Dance" 1998 (Box 15)
      - "Dinner Dance" 1999 (Box 15)
      - "65th Anniversary Year Commemoration" Dinner Dance 2000 (Box 15)
      - "Dinner Dance" 2001 (Box 15)
    - Summer Barbeque
      - "Swim Party - Barbecue" 1991 (Box 15)
      - "Barbecue Swim Party" 1992 (Box 15)
      - "Barbecue Swim Party" 1993 (Box 15)
      - "BBQ Swim Party" 194 (Box 15)
      - "Barbecue Party" 1995 (Box 15)
      - "Barbecue" 1996 (Box 15)
      - "Assoc. Swim Party BBQ" 1998 (Box 15)
      - "BBQ" 1999 (Box 15)
      - "Barbecue" 2000 (Box 15)
    - Other Events
      - "Las Vegas Night and Barbeque" 1988 (Box 15)
      - Dinner Social 1990 (Box 15)
      - "Assoc. Annual Meeting and Dinner" 1992 (Box 15)
      - "Training Academy Dedication 1992 (Box 15)
      - Chief Dove's Dinner 1993 (Box 15)
      - "Hawkins Good-by Reception" 1993 (Box 15)
      - "President's Fund Receipts" 1995-1999 (Box 15)
  - Photographs
    - 1951, 1953, 1954, n.d. (Box 15)
    - 1959-1963, n.d. (Box 15)
- Other Companies
  - Station 1 - Arington 1998 (Box 15)
  - Station 2 - Ballston 1991, 1992 (Box 15)
  - Station 4 - Clarendon 1984 (Box 15)
  - Station 7 - Fairington 1992 (Box 15)